Guide to the James Graham Phelps Stokes Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
James Graham Phelps Stokes papers
1889-1910
MS 1587
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
2.5
(6 boxes)
The papers consist primarily of correspondence of James Graham Phelps Stokes and Rose Harriet Pastor Stokes between 1903 and 1910. Correspondents include personal friends, family members, and colleagues active in social reform work and the Socialist Party. Invitations to speaking engagements and arrangements for public appearances are the subjects of many of these letters.
Stokes, James Graham Phelps, 1872-1960
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The papers were purchased from Charles Apfelbaum, 1990.
Arrangement
Arranged in two series: I. James Graham Phelps Stokes Files, 1889-1910. II. Rose Pastor Stokes Files, 1904-1910.
Scope and Contents
The James Graham Phelps Stokes Papers consist primarily of incoming letters addressed to James Graham Phelps Stokes and to his wife Rose Harriet Pastor Stokes between the years of 1903 and 1910. Very few outgoing responses are included in these papers. While obviously not a complete record of the period, the papers help document Stokes's social reform activities and his increasing involvement in the Socialist Party, as well as the early years of his marriage and the popularity of both husband and wife as speakers and writers. The papers augment collections of James Graham Phelps Stokes Papers at Columbia University and of Rose Pastor Stokes Papers in the Manuscripts and Archives Department and in the Tamiment Library.
The papers, which were purchased from Charles Apfelbaum in 1990, are arranged in two series: I. JAMES GRAHAM PHELPS STOKES FILES, 1889-1910 and II. ROSE PASTOR STOKES FILES, 1904-1910.
Both series include correspondence, as well as small quantities of bills and receipts, writings, and memorabilia. Letters addressed to both husband and wife are arranged in the files of James Graham Phelps Stokes, as are all letters from members of the Stokes family.
Series I, JAMES GRAHAM PHELPS STOKES FILES, is the larger of the two series, with correspondence and general files comprising the bulk of the series. Correspondents include personal friends, family members, and colleagues active in social reform work and the Socialist Party. In addition to incoming letters, the files also may include records of committees on which Stokes served, brochures and other printed material concerning charitable and political organizations, program announcements, and clippings. These files include numerous invitations to speak with subsequent details concerning arrangements.
Among the larger files are those for the National Conference of Charities and Corrections and the New York Association for Improving the Condition of the Poor. For the former there are records kept by Stokes as treasurer and for the latter there are materials relating to the finances of Hartley House and monthly statistical reports concerning the work of the association's Department of Relief. Other letters concerning Stokes's interest in the settlement house movement will be found in the files for various settlement houses. Housing conditions are the subject of Robert W. De Forest's letters, while the eight hour working day is discussed in correspondence with Commissioner Sherman of the New York State Department of Labor. A smaller number of letters relating to Stokes's business and the Nevada Company is included in the file for James McCulloch.
While Stokes was active in politics as a candidate supporting William Randolph Hearst, there is little in these files on the subject. The files for the New York American and the New York Journal are relevant, while letters from William Earl Dodge Stokes comment on his nephew's political decisions, including his membership in the Socialist Party.
Series II, ROSE PASTOR STOKES FILES, is similar in content to that for her husband, though smaller in quantity. The bulk of this material concerns speaking engagements and writings. There are few exchanges with personal friends; there does not appear to be any correspondence with members of the Pastor family, though there are a number of unidentified letters.
Biographical / Historical
James Graham Phelps Stokes was born in New York City on March 18, 1872. He was the son of Anson Phelps and Helen Louise (Phelps) Stokes. Family members included leaders in New York society, who had derived their fortune from the Phelps-Dodge Company and subsequent railroad and real estate holdings. The family had a long history of interest in religious and philanthropic activities and had been particularly active in the American Board of Commissioners for Foreign Missions, the American Bible Society, and the American Tract Society.
Stokes was educated at the Berkeley School in New York City and entered Yale's Sheffield Scientific School as a member of the class of 1892. While at Yale he was director of the Cooperative Society and a member of the executive board of the YMCA. After graduation he spent a year traveling and then entered the College of Physicians and Surgeons at Columbia with the class of 1896. In medicine he hoped to combine his religious and scientific interest to become a medical missionary. While a medical student he served as an ambulance surgeon at Roosevelt Hospital, which covered Hell's Kitchen, and from this experience he came to be interested in the environmental influences on disease. Stokes perceived that the roots of the conditions in Hell's Kitchen were intimately related to the great disparities of wealth in American society.
Upon graduation he had to forego his desire to enter the missionary field to replace his ailing father in the family business. Eventually he served as president of the Nevada Company and the Nevada Central Railroad and, after 1927, as a member of the board of directors of the Phelps-Dodge Company. Stokes combined his entry into business with a year of study of political science at Columbia. But, in the years after 1897, settlement house work became the focus of his life. He served on the board of directors of the University Settlement and immersed himself in the study of life on the Lower East Side.
After serving in the Spanish-American War, Stokes returned to reform work. He served on innumerable boards, including those of the Outdoor Recreational League of New York, the Prison Association of New York (he eventually became a state inspector of prisons and a delegate to the International Prison Congress of 1905), the League of Political Education, the Citizens' Union, the New York State Conference of Charities and Correction, the New York Child Labor Committee, and Tuskeegee Institute. He also was a founder and chairman of the board of trustees (1897-1917) of Hartley House, a settlement house on West 46th Street.
After 1902 he lived at the University Settlement. It was here that he met Rose Harriet Pastor, a former cigar worker and militant reporter for the Jewish Daily News, who would become his wife in the much publicized marriage of the "Millionaire and the Factory Girl." At this time Stokes was evolving a collectivist philosophy which he called "Omnilism," one which looked "primarily to the Well-being of the Whole which Others and Self are but parts" and called for dedication to the advancement of the whole. This philosophy and his activist wife led him to politics and socialism.
In 1904 Stokes was a presidential elector on the Populist ticket, and in 1905, running on the Municipal Ownership League ticket headed by William Randolph Hearst, he was nearly elected president of the Board of Alderman of New York City. He joined the Socialist Party in 1906 and was a founder of the Intercollegiate Socialist Society, serving as its president from 1907 to 1917. In 1907 he renounced the concept of philanthropy in favor of the collective ownership of capital for the public welfare, and in 1908 he was elected to the National Executive Committee of the Socialist Party. In the same year he ran for the New York State Senate on the Socialist ticket. He also was one of the participants in the 1909 meeting on the status of the Negro, which led to the calling of the National Negro Congress and the founding of the National Association for the Advancement of colored People (NAACP). In 1912 he ran for mayor of Stamford, Connecticut, on the Socialist ticket, and in 1916 he helped edit The Socialism of Today.
The question of American intervention in World War I split the Socialist Party. Stokes promoted the war effort as a founding member of the American Alliance for Labor and Democracy. His wife opposed the war and moved towards communism. Their ideological split led to a divorce in 1925. In the years after the war, Stokes became progressively more conservative and increasingly centered his attention on veterans and on cultural and philanthropic activities. In 1926 he married Lettice Lee Sands. He devoted his later years to the study of religions and published two books on Christianity and the religions of the East. Stokes died in New York City on April 8, 1960.
Extracted from: Biographical Dictionary of Social Welfare in America, (Westport, CT: Greenwood Press), 1986.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Radicalism; Social settlements -- United States; Socialism; De Forest, Robert W. (Robert Weeks), 1848-1931; Hearst, William Randolph, 1863-1951; Stokes, James Graham Phelps, 1872-1960; Stokes, Rose Pastor, 1879-1933; National Conference of Charities and Correction (U.S.); New York Association for Improving the Condition of the Poor; Socialist Party (U.S.)
- JAMES GRAHAM PHELPS STOKES FILES, 1889, 1896-1910, undated; Series I; 1.75' (4 boxes)
  Scope and Contents
  The files in this series are arranged by record type. The files of correspondence and general files, which appear at the beginning of the series, are arranged alphabetically by personal or corporate name.
  - Correspondence/general files
    - Ab - American E (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - American M - Ay (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Adler, Felix, 1903-1905, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Adler, Helen (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Ajax Committee, 1903-1904 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Armstrong Association, 1902-1904, 1906 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Ba - Ber (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Bes - Bu (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Bamford, Frederick Irons
      General
      See: box 3, folder 66
    - Bh치rati, B치b치 Prem치nand, 1903-1904 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Blatch, Harriot Stanton
      See: box 1, folder 18
    - Ca - Ch (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Ci - Cu (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Casson, Herbert
      See: box 2, folder 49
      See:box 2, folders 47
    - Charity Organization Society of the City of New York, 1903-1905 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Chautauqua Institution, 1907 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Chicago Commons, 1903-1904 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Contemporary Club, 1906, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - D (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - De Forest, Robert W., 1903 January-Dec, undated (Box 1, Folder 16-17)
    - E (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - F (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Fitzgerald, Susan W.
      See: box 4, folder 94
      See: box 3, folders 62
    - G (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Had - Han (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Har - Hu (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Hadden, Alexander, 1903-1904 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Hammond, Emily, undated (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Hartley House
      See: box 2, folders 50-51
    - Henry Romeike, Ltd., 1902, 1904, 1906 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Holme, Sara, 1904 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Hoyt, Ethel Phelps Stokes
      See: box 3, folder 79
    - I (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Independent, 1903-1904 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - International Peace Congress
      See: box 2, folder 42
    - J (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - Johnson, Alexander
      See: box 2, folder 46
    - Ka - Ke (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - Ki - Ku (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - Kelly, Edmond, 1906-1907, undated (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - Knopf, S. A., 1905-1907 (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - L (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - Lanier, Sidney, 1907 (Box 2, Folder 35)
    - League for Political Education, 1905-1907 (Box 2, Folder 36)
    - League of American Sportsmen, 1907, undated (Box 2, Folder 37)
    - Leeds, John B., 1906-1907 (Box 2, Folder 38)
    - Lemon, Courtney, 1907 (Box 2, Folder 39)
    - M (Box 2, Folder 40)
    - McCulloch, James, 1907 (Box 2, Folder 41)
    - Mead, Edwin D., 1902-1904, undated (Box 2, Folder 42)
    - Na - New Jersey (Box 2, Folder 43)
    - New York - Nu (Box 2, Folder 44)
    - National Arts Club, 1904-1905 (Box 2, Folder 45)
    - National Conference of Charities and Correction, 1904-1905, 1907, undated (Box 2, Folder 46)
    - New Era Club, 1904-1905, 1907, undated (Box 2, Folder 47)
    - New York, City of Tenement House Department
      See: box 1, folder 17
    - New York, State Department of Labor, 1906 (Box 2, Folder 48)
    - New York American; New York Journal, 1904,1907 (Box 2, Folder 49)
    - New York Association for Improving the Condition of the Poor, 1901-1903 September-Oct, 1905, undated (Box 2, Folder 50)
    - New York Association for Improving the Condition of the Poor, 1901-1903 September-Oct, 1905, undated (Box 2, Folder 51)
    - New York Journal
    - New York World, 1905-1907 (Box 3, Folder 52)
    - O (Box 3, Folder 53)
    - Ovington, Mary White, 1904 (Box 3, Folder 54)
    - P (Box 3, Folder 55)
    - People's Institute
      See: box 5, folder 151
    - Port Chester Women's Club, 1905-1906, undated (Box 3, Folder 56)
    - Q (Box 3, Folder 57)
    - Ra - Ri (Box 3, Folder 58)
    - Ro - Ry (Box 3, Folder 59)
    - Raritan Club, 1906-1907 (Box 3, Folder 60)
    - Reynolds, Stephen Marion, 1909-1910, undated (Box 3, Folder 61)
    - Richmond Hill House, 1903-1907, undated (Box 3, Folder 62)
    - Riedell, John William, 1904, 1906-1907 (Box 3, Folder 63)
    - Riordan, Raymond, 1904-1905, undated (Box 3, Folder 64)
    - Robbins, Jane E., 1903-1904, undated (Box 3, Folder 65)
    - Rood, Grace
      See: box 3, folder 56
    - Ruskin Club, undated (Box 3, Folder 66)
    - Sa - Sh (Box 3, Folder 67)
    - Si - Sp (Box 3, Folder 68)
    - St - Sy (Box 3, Folder 69)
    - Socialist Party (United States)
      - General, 1904, 1906-1907, 1910 (Box 3, Folder 70)
      - New Jersey locals, 1904, 1906-1907 (Box 3, Folder 71)
      - New York City committees, locals, 1905-1909, undated (Box 3, Folder 72)
      - New York State committees, misc. locals, 1906, 1907 (Box 3, Folder 73)
      - Ruskin Club
      - Other locals, 1906-1907 (Box 3, Folder 74)
    - Society for Ethical Culture
      See: box 1, folder 3
    - Soubiros, A., 1906, undated (Box 3, Folder 75)
    - Spargo, John, 1906, undated (Box 3, Folder 76)
    - Stokes family: general, 1906, undated (Box 3, Folder 77)
    - Stokes, Anson Greene Phelps, 1905-1907, undated (Box 3, Folder 78)
    - Stokes, Helen Louisa Phelps, 1905-1906, 1910, undated (Box 3, Folder 80)
    - Stokes, Olivia Phelps, 1906, undated (Box 3, Folder 81)
    - Stokes, Rose H. Pastor, 1904-1905 (Box 4, Folder 82)
    - Stokes, William Earl Dodge, 1905-1906 (Box 4, Folder 83)
      - Tarbell, Ida, 1904, undated (Box 4, Folder 87)
    - Straight Edge Industrial Settlement; "Straight Edge Movement", 1905-1907 (Box 4, Folder 84)
    - Ta - Th (Box 4, Folder 85)
    - Ti - Ty (Box 4, Folder 86)
    - Thomas, Elizabeth H., 1907 (Box 4, Folder 88)
    - Tiffany and Co., 1905 (Box 4, Folder 89)
    - Topper, William, 1903-1904, undated (Box 4, Folder 90)
    - Tucker, Preble, 1902, 1904 (Box 4, Folder 91)
    - U (Box 4, Folder 92)
      - Stokes, Ethel V. Phelps, 1906, undated (Box 3, Folder 79)
    - University Settlement Society of New York
      - Eldridge Street Branch; McDougal Street Branch, 1903, 1905, undated (Box 4, Folder 93)
      - West Side Branch, 1903, 1905, undated (Box 4, Folder 94)
    - V (Box 4, Folder 95)
    - Vedanta Society, 1905-1906 (Box 4, Folder 96)
    - Wa - Wh (Box 4, Folder 97)
    - Wi - Wy (Box 4, Folder 98)
    - Wald, Lillian D., 1904-1905 (Box 4, Folder 99)
    - Walling, Anna Strunsky, 1906 (Box 4, Folder 100)
    - Walling, William English, 1906-1907, undated (Box 4, Folder 101)
    - Weeks, Rufus, 1906-1907 (Box 4, Folder 102)
    - West Side Neighborhood House, 1903-1904 (Box 4, Folder 103)
    - Weyl, Walter, 1905, 1907 (Box 4, Folder 104)
    - Wilshire, Gaylord Wilshire, Mary Wilshire's Magazine, 1905-1906 (Box 4, Folder 105)
    - Wolbarst, Abraham L.
      See: box 2, folders 47
    - Women's Club of Port Chester
    - X - Y - Z (Box 4, Folder 106)
    - Unidentified, 1903-1908, undated (Box 4, Folder 107)
  - Bills and receipts: domestic, 1903, 1905-1907, undated (Box 4, Folder 108)
  - Genealogical records (Box 7)
  - Memorabilia, 1889 (Box 4, Folder 109)
  - Printed matter, 1896, 1903, 1905-1906, undated (Box 4, Folder 110)
  - Writings, 1897, 1904-1910, undated (Box 4, Folder 111)
- ROSE PASTOR STOKES FILES, 1904-1910, undated; Series II; .75' (2 boxes)
  - Correspondence/general files
    - A (Box 5, Folder 112)
    - Alumnae Association of the Girls' High and Normal Schools of Philadelphia, 1906-1907 (Box 5, Folder 113)
    - American Academy of Political and Social Science, 1906, undated (Box 5, Folder 114)
    - B (Box 5, Folder 115)
    - Barnum, Gertrude
      See: box 6, folder 177
    - Barrows, C. ("Aunt Isabel"), 1907 (Box 5, Folder 116)
    - C (Box 5, Folder 117)
    - Cahan, Abraham
      See: box 5, folder 124
    - Charles H. Kerr and Co., 1904, 1907 (Box 5, Folder 118)
    - Conger-Kaneko, Josephine
      See: box 6, folder 158
    - D-E (Box 5, Folder 119)
    - F (Box 5, Folder 120)
    - G (Box 5, Folder 121)
    - H (Box 5, Folder 122)
    - Henry Street Settlement, 1910 (Box 5, Folder 123)
    - I-J (Box 5, Folder 124)
    - Jewish Daily Forward, 1907 (Box 5, Folder 125)
    - K (Box 5, Folder 126)
    - Kiefer, Daniel, 1906-1907 (Box 5, Folder 127)
    - L (Box 5, Folder 128)
    - Lee, Algernon, 1907 (Box 5, Folder 129)
    - Levien, Sara, 1907 (Box 5, Folder 130)
    - M (Box 5, Folder 131)
    - N-O (Box 5, Folder 132)
    - National American Women Suffrage Association, 1909 (Box 5, Folder 133)
    - O'Sheal, Shaemas, 1910 (Box 5, Folder 134)
    - P (Box 5, Folder 135)
    - People's Institute
    - Phelps, Mary, 1910, undated (Box 5, Folder 136)
    - Pike, Violet
    - Pultz, Alfred, 1910 (Box 5, Folder 137)
    - Q (Box 5, Folder 138)
    - R (Box 5, Folder 139)
    - Rauh, Flora, 1905-1906, undated (Box 5, Folder 140)
    - Rauh, Ida, undated (Box 5, Folder 141)
      See also: box 6, folder 177
    - Rivkin, Mamie, 1909 (Box 5, Folder 142)
    - Rowe, L. S.
      See: box 5, folder 114
    - Rutnam, S. C. Kanaga, 1908 (Box 5, Folder 143)
    - Sa - Sl (Box 5, Folder 144)
    - Sm - Su (Box 5, Folder 145)
    - Samuels, Adelaide
    - Sanford, Mary R., 1909, undated (Box 5, Folder 146)
    - Serge, Anna, 1905-1906 (Box 5, Folder 147)
    - Shelley, Marie C., 1905-1906 (Box 5, Folder 148)
    - Simpson, Daisy Simpson, M. S., 1905-1906, undated (Box 5, Folder 149)
    - Slosson, Edwin E., 1906, 1908 (Box 5, Folder 150)
    - Smith, Charles Sprague Smith, Isabelle Dwight, 1905-1906, 1908, 1910, undated (Box 5, Folder 151)
    - Smith, Hyacinth, undated (Box 5, Folder 152)
    - Socialist Party (United States)
      - National Committee, 1908, 1910 (Box 6, Folder 153)
      - New York City locals, 1907, 1909, 1910 (Box 6, Folder 154)
      - New York State locals, 1907-1910 (Box 6, Folder 155)
      - Pennsylvania State Committee, 1906, 1910 (Box 6, Folder 156)
      - Miscellaneous locals, 1907 (Box 6, Folder 157)
    - Socialist Woman, 1907 (Box 6, Folder 158)
    - Starr, Ellen G., 1905-1906 (Box 6, Folder 159)
    - Stewart, Laura, 1906, undated (Box 6, Folder 160)
    - Stokes family
      See: box 3, folders 77-83
    - T (Box 6, Folder 161)
    - Taylor, Annie B., 1908-1910 (Box 6, Folder 162)
    - Thayer, Gladys, 1910, undated (Box 6, Folder 163)
    - Trautmann, Mary E.
      See: box 6, folder 176
    - U (Box 6, Folder 164)
    - United Hebrew Charities of the City of New York, 1905-1906 (Box 6, Folder 165)
    - Untermeyer, Minnie, undated (Box 6, Folder 166)
    - V (Box 6, Folder 167)
    - Wa - Wh (Box 6, Folder 168)
    - Wi - Wo (Box 6, Folder 169)
    - Walling, Anna Strunsky, 1907 (Box 6, Folder 170)
    - Weislander, S., 1906-1907 (Box 6, Folder 171)
    - Welch, Eunice
      See: box 5, folder 131
    - Wentworth, H. Lucetta, 1905-1906 (Box 6, Folder 172)
    - White, James T., 1906, undated (Box 6, Folder 173)
    - Wilson, J. Stitt, 1906-1907, undated (Box 6, Folder 174)
    - Women's Club of Glen Ridge, New Jersey, 1907, undated (Box 6, Folder 175)
    - Women's Health Protective Association of New York, 1906-1907, undated (Box 6, Folder 176)
    - Women's Trade Union League, 1905-1910, undated (Box 6, Folder 177)
    - Younger, Maud, 1906-1907 (Box 6, Folder 178)
    - "Miriam", 1908, undated (Box 6, Folder 181)
    - Z (Box 6, Folder 179)
    - Unidentified
      - General, 1905-1909, undated (Box 6, Folder 180)
      - "Yetta", 1905-1907, undated (Box 6, Folder 182)
  - Bills and receipts: domestic, 1905-1908, undated (Box 6, Folder 183)
  - Memorabilia, 1904, undated (Box 6, Folder 184)
  - Printed matter, 1904 (Box 6, Folder 185)
  - Writings, 1904-1905, 1910, undated (Box 6, Folder 186)